<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties answer to the XIX. propositions of both Houses of Parliament.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E151_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10823</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858891</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110951</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110951)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E151[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties answer to the XIX. propositions of both Houses of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>Colepeper, John Colepeper, Baron, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Falkland, Lucius Cary, Viscount, 1610?-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majestie: And by the Assignes of John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The humble petition and advice of both Houses of Parliament, with XIX propositions, and the conclusion. Sent unto his Majestie, the second of June, 1642.</note>
                  <note>According to Clarendon (Life (1857) v.1, p.130-31), the answer was actually written by Sir John Colepeper and Viscount Falkland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110951:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110951:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His Majeſties ANSWER TO THE XIX. PROPOSITIONS OF BOTH <hi>HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES</hi> OF Parliament.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie: And by the Aſſignes of JOHN BILL. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110951:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110951:2"/>
            <head>His Majeſties Anſwer To the nineteen PROPOSITIONS of both Houſes of Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore We ſhall give you Our Anſwer to your Petition and Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, We ſhall tell you, that We are now cleary ſatisfied, why the Method, which We traced out to you by Our Meſſage of the <hi>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of Ianuary, and have ſince ſo often preſſed upon you, as the proper way to compoſe the diſtractions of this Kingdom, and render it truly happy, hath been hitherto declined, and is at length thought fit to be looked upon; We now ſee plainly (and deſire that you, and all other Our good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould do ſo too) that the Cabaliſts of this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe have with great Prudence reſerved themſelves, untill due preparations ſhould be made for their Deſigne.</p>
            <p>If they had unſeaſonably vented ſuch Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the Wiſdom and Modeſtie of your Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours never thought fit to offer to any of Our Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours, nor We in honour or regard to Our Regall authority (which God hath entruſted Vs with for the good of Our People) could receive without juſt indignation (and ſuch many of your preſent Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110951:3"/> are) their hopes would ſoon have been blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thoſe Perſons, to whom Offices, Honours, Power and Commands were deſigned, by ſuch ill timing of their buſineſſe, would have failed of their expectation, not without a Brand upon the attempt. Therefore, before any of this nature ſhould appear, they have (certainly with great wiſdom in the <abbr>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</abbr> of it) thought fit to remove a troubleſome Rub in their way, <hi>The Law;</hi> To this end, (that they might undermine the very foundations of it) a new Power hath been aſſumed to interpret and declare Laws without Vs by extemporary Votes, without any Caſe judicially before either Houſe, (which is in effect the ſame thing as to make Laws without Vs) Orders and Ordinances made onely by both Houſes (tending to a pure arbitrary power) were preſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people as Laws, and their obedience required to them.</p>
            <p>Their next ſtep was, To erect an upſtart Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without Vs, (in whom, and onely in whom the Laws of this Realm have placed that Power) To command the <hi>Militia,</hi> (very conſiderable to this their Deſigne;) In further order to it they have wreſted from Vs Our Magazin and town of <hi>Hull,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtridde Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> in his bold-faced Treaſon; They have prepared and directed to the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſidented Invectives againſt Our Government, thereby (as much as lay in their power) to weaken Our juſt Authority and due eſteem among them; They have as injuriouſly as preſumptuouſly (though We conceive by this time Impudence it ſelf is aſhamed of it) attempted to caſt upon Vs aſperſions of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of nature, as if We had <hi>favoured a Rebellion in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110951:3"/> Our own Bowels;</hi> They have likewiſe broached new Doctrine, <hi>That We are obliged to paſſe all Laws that ſhall be offered to Us by both Houſes</hi> (howſoever Our own Iudgement and Conſcience ſhall be unſatisfied with them) a point of Policie, as proper for their preſent buſineſſe, as deſtructive to all Our Rights of Parliament; And ſo with ſtrange ſhameleſneſſe will forget a Clauſe in a Law ſtill in force, made in the ſecond yeer of King <hi>H. 5.</hi> wherein both Houſes of Parliament do acknowledge, <hi>That it is of the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality to grant or deny ſuch of their Petitions as pleaſeth Himſelf,</hi> They have interpreted Our neceſſary Guard, legally aſſembled for the Defence of Vs and Our Childrens Perſons againſt a Traitour in open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt Vs, to be <hi>with intent to leavie War againſt Our Parliament,</hi> (the thought whereof Our very ſoul abhorreth) thereby to render Vs odious to Our People.</p>
            <p>They have ſo awed Our good Subjects with Purſivants, long chargeable Attendance, Heavie Cenſures and illegall Impriſonments, that few of them durſt offer to preſent their tenderneſſe of Our Sufferings, their own juſt Grievances, and their ſenſe of thoſe violations of the Law, (the Birthright of every Subject of this Kingdom) though in an humble Petition directed to both Houſes; and if any did, it was ſtifled in the Birth, called <hi>Sedition,</hi> and burnt by the common Hangman.</p>
            <p>They have refrained the Attendance of Our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and neceſſary Houſhold-ſervants, and ſeized up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe ſmall ſums of Money which Our Credit had provided to buy Vs Bread, With Injunctions That none ſhall be ſuffered to be conveyed or returned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110951:4"/> to Vs to <hi>York,</hi> or any of Our Peers or Servants with Vs, ſo that (in effect) they have blocked Vs up in that County.</p>
            <p>They have filled the ears of the People with the noiſe of Feares and Iealouſies, (though taken up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt) tales of Skippers, Salt-Fleets, and ſuch like, by which Alarms they might prepare them to receive ſuch impreſſions, as might beſt advance this Deſigne when it ſhould be ripe. And now it ſeemes they think We are ſufficiently prepared for theſe bitter Pills, We are in a handſome Poſture to receive theſe <hi>humble Deſires,</hi> (which probably are intended to make way for a Superfetation of a (yet) higher nature, (if We had not made this diſcovery to you) for they do not tell Vs this is all. In them We muſt obſerve that theſe Contrivers (the better to advance their true ends) diſguiſed as much as they could their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents with a mixture of ſome things really to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by every honeſt man; Others, ſpecious and popular; And ſome which are already granted by Vs; All which are cunningly twiſted and mixed with thoſe other things of their main Deſigne of Ambition and private intereſt; in hope, that at the firſt view, every eye may not ſo cleerly diſcerne them in their proper colours.</p>
            <p>We would not be underſtood, That We intend to fix this Deſigne upon both, or either Houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; We utterly profeſſe againſt it, being moſt confident of the Loyalty, good affections and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the intentions of that great Bodie, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well that very many of both Houſes were abſent, and many diſſented from all thoſe particulars We complain of: But We do beleeve, and accordingly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110951:4"/> profeſſe to all the world, that the Malignity of this Deſigne (as dangerous to the Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Peace of the ſame, and the Liberties of all Our good Subjects, as to Our Selfe, and Our juſt Prerogative) hath proceeded from the ſubtill Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, miſchievous Practices, and evill Counſels of ambitious turbulent Spirits, diſaffected to Gods true Religion, and the Vnity of the Profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Our Honour and Safety, and the publike Peace and proſperity of Our people, not without a ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the very actions of both Houſes. But how faulty ſoever others are, We ſhall (with Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) endeavour to diſcharge Our duty with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart; And therefore ſince theſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions come to Vs in the name of both Houſes of Parliament, We ſhall take a more particular notice of every of them.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 9. 10. 15. 16. 19.</hi> Demands had been writ and printed in a tongue unknown to Vs and Our people, it might have been poſſible We and they might have charitably beleeved the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be ſuch as might have been in Order to the ends pretended in the Petition (to wit) <hi>the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Our Honour and Safety, the welfare and Security of Our Subjects and Dominions, and the removing thoſe Jealouſies and Differences which are ſaid to have unhappily fallen betwixt Us and Our people, and procuring both Us and them a conſtant courſe of Honour, Peace and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> But being read and underſtood by all, We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but aſſure Our Self that this Profeſſion, joyned to theſe Propoſitions, will rather appear a Mockery and a Scorne; The Demands being ſuch, as We were unworthy of the truſt repoſed in Vs by the Law,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110951:5"/> and of Our Deſcent from ſo many great and famous Anceſtours, if We could be brought to abandon that power which onely can inable Vs to performe what We are ſworne to, in protecting Our People and the Lawes, and ſo aſſume others into it, as to deveſt Our ſelf of it; Although not onely Our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition (which it can hardly be) were more neceſſitous then it is, and We were both vanquiſht, and a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp; in a worſe condition then ever the moſt unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate of Our Predeceſſours have been reduced to, by the moſt criminall of their Subjects; And though the Bait laid to draw Vs to it, and to keep Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from indignation at the mention of it, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes <hi>of a plentifull and unparaleld Revenue,</hi> were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from generals (which ſignifie nothing) to cleer and certain particulars, ſince ſuch a Bargain would have but too great a reſemblance of that of <hi>Eſaus,</hi> if We ſhould part with ſuch Flowers of Our Crowne, as are worth all the reſt of the Garland, and have been tranſmitted to Vs from ſo many Anceſtours, and have been found ſo uſefull and neceſſary for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Security of Our Subjects, for any preſent neceſſity, or for any low and ſordid Conſiderations of Wealth and gain. And therefore all men knowing that thoſe Accommodations are moſt eaſily made, and moſt exactly obſerved, that are grounded upon reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and equall Conditions, We have great Cauſe to beleeve, that the Contrivers of theſe had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of ſetling any firm Accommodation but to increaſe thoſe Iealouſies, and widen that diviſion, which (not by Our fault) is now unhappily fallen betweene Vs and both Houſes.</p>
            <p>It is aſked, <hi>That all the Lords and others of Our privy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110951:5"/> Councell, and ſuch</hi> (We know now what you mean by <hi>ſuch,</hi> but We have cauſe to think you mean <hi>all) great Officers and Miniſters of State, either at home or beyond the Seas,</hi> (For care is taken to leave out no Perſon or place, that Our diſhonour may be ſure not to be bounded within this Kingdom, though no ſubtile Inſinuations at ſuch a diſtance can probably be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved to have been the cauſe of Our diſtractions and dangers) <hi>ſhould be put from Our Privy Councell, and from thoſe Offices and imployments, unleſſe they be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> how faithfull ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever We have found them to Vs and the publike, and how far ſoever they have been from offending againſt any Law, the onely rule they had or any others ought to have to walk by. We therefore to this part of this demand return you this Anſwer, That we are willing to grant that they ſhall take a larger Oath then you yours ſelves deſire in your <hi>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> Demand, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining not of any part but of the whole Law; And We have and do aſſure you, That We will be carefull to make election of ſuch perſons in thoſe places of truſt, as ſhall have given good teſtimonies of their abilities and integrities, and againſt whom there can be no juſt cauſe of exception, whereon reaſonably to ground a diffidence; That if We have or ſhall be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in Our election, We have and do aſſure you, that there is no man ſo near to Vs in place or affection, whom we will not leave to the Iuſtice of the Law, if you ſhall bring a particular charge &amp; ſufficient proofs againſt him; And that We have given you (the beſt pledge of the effects of ſuch a promiſe on Our part, and the beſt ſecurity for the performance of their duty on theirs) <hi>a Trienniall Parliament,</hi> the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110951:6"/> of whoſe Iuſtice will in all probability make them wary how they provoke it, and Vs wary how We chuſe ſuch, as by the diſcovery of their faults may in any degree ſeem to diſcredit Our election. But that without any ſhadow of a fault objected, only perhaps becauſe they follow their conſcience, and preſerve the eſtabliſhed Laws, and agree not in ſuch Votes, or aſſent not to ſuch Bils, as ſome perſons, who have now too great an Influence even upon both Houſes, judge or ſeem to judge to be for the publike good, and as are agreeable to that new <hi>Utopia</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Government into which they endeavour to transform this Kingdom; (for We remember what names, and for what Reaſons you left out in the Bill offered Vs concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> which you had your ſelves recommended in the Ordinance) We will never conſent to the diſplacing of any, whom for their former merits from, and affection to Vs and the publike, We have intruſted, ſince We conceive, That to do ſo, would take away both from the affection of Our ſervants the care of Our ſervice, and the Honour of Our Iuſtice. And We the more wonder, That it ſhould be aſkt by you of Vs, ſince it appears by the <hi>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> Demand, That your ſelves count it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, after the preſent turn is ſerved, <hi>that the Judges and Officers who are then placed may hold their places <hi>quàm diu ſe bene geſſerint.</hi>
               </hi> And We are reſolved to be as carefull of thoſe We have choſen, as you are of thoſe you would chuſe, and to remove none, till they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to Vs to have otherwiſe behaved themſelves, or ſhall be evicted by legall proceedings to have done ſo.</p>
            <p>But this Demand (as unreaſonable as it is) is but one link of a great Chaine, and but the firſt round of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110951:6"/> that Ladder, by which Our Iuſt, Ancient, Regall Power is endeavoured to be fetched down to the ground. For it appears plainly, that it is not with the perſons now choſen, but with Our chooſing that you are diſpleaſed; For you demand, <hi>That the perſons put into the places &amp; imployments of thoſe who ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, may be approved by both Houſes;</hi> which is ſo far (as to ſome it may at firſt ſight appear) from being leſſe then the power of nomination, that of two things (of which We will never grant either) We would ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be content that you ſhould nominate and We ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, then you approve and We nominate; The meer nomination being ſo far from being any thing, that if We could do no more, We would never take the paines to do that, when We ſhould onely hazard thoſe, whom We eſteemed, to the ſcorn of a refuſall, if they hapned not to be agreeable not onely to the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to the paſſion, intereſt or humor of the preſent major part of either Houſe. Not to ſpeak now of the great factions, animoſities and diviſions which this power would introduce in both Houſes, between both Houſes, and in the ſeverall Countries, for the choice of perſons to be ſent to that place where that power was, and between the perſons that were ſo choſen. Neither is this ſtrange Potion preſcribed to Vs onely for once, for the cure of a preſent, preſſing, deſperate diſeaſe, but for a dyet to Vs and Our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; It is demanded, <hi>That Our Councellors, all Chief Officers both of Law and State, Commanders of Forts and Caſtles, and all Peers hereafter made</hi> (as to voting, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which how little is the reſt?) <hi>be approved of</hi> (that is, choſen <hi>by them from time to time;</hi> and rather then it ſhould ever be left to the Crown (to whom it onely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110951:7"/> doth and ſhall belong) <hi>if any place fall voyd in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Parliament, the major part of the approved Councell is to approve them.</hi> Neither is it onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that We ſhould quit the Power and Right Our Predeceſſors have had of appointing Perſons in theſe places, but for Councellors We are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, as well in the number, as in the perſons, and a power muſt be annext to theſe places, which their Predeceſſors had not; And indeed if this power were paſt to them, it were not fit We ſhould be truſted to chooſe thoſe, who were to be truſted as much as We.</p>
            <p>It is demanded, <hi>That ſuch matters as concern the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and are proper for the high Court of Parliament,</hi> (which is Our Great and Supream Councell) <hi>may be debated, reſolved and tranſacted onely in Parliament, and not elſwhere, and ſuch as preſume to do any thing to the contrary ſhall be reſerved to the Cenſure and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Parliament, and ſuch other matters of State, as are proper for Our Privy Councell, ſhall be debated and concluded by ſuch of Our Nobility</hi> (though indeed, if being made by Vs they may not vote without the Conſent of both Houſes, We are rather to call them your Nobility) <hi>and others, as ſhall be from time to time choſen for that place, by approbation of both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and that no publike Act concerning the affairs of the Kingdom, which are proper for Our Privie Councell, may be eſteemed of any validity, as proceeding from the Royall Authority, unleſſe it be done by the Advice and Conſent of the major part of Our Councell, atteſted under their hands:</hi> Which Demands are of that Nature, that to grant them were in effect at once to depoſe both Our Self and Our Poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Theſe being paſt, We may be waited on bare-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110951:7"/> We may have Our hand kiſt; The Style of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie continued to Vs; And the Kings Authoritie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by both Houſes of Parliament, may be ſtill the Style of your Commands; We may have Swords and Maces carried before Vs, and pleaſe Our Self with the ſight of a Crown and Scepter, (and yet even theſe Twigs would not long flouriſh, when the Stock upon which they grew were dead) but as to true and reall Power We ſhould remain but the outſide, but the Picture, but the ſigne of a King. We were ever willing that Our Parliament ſhould debate, reſolve, and tranſact ſuch matters as are proper for them, as far as they are proper for them: And We heartily wiſh, that they would be as carefull not to extend their Debates and Reſolutions beyond what is proper to them, that multitudes of things puniſhable, and cauſes determinable by the Ordinary Iudicatures, may not be enterteined in Parliament, and ſo cauſe a long, chargeable, fruitleſſe attendance of Our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and (by Degrees) draw to you as well all the cauſes, as all the faults of <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert your proper buſineſſe; That the courſe of Law be no wayes diverted, much leſſe diſturbed, as was actually done by the ſtop of the proceedings againſt a Riot in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> by Order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, in a time ſo riotous and tumultuous, as much increaſed the danger of Popular inſolencies, by ſuch a countenance to Riots, and diſcountenance of Law; That you deſcend not to the leaſure of recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lecturers to Churches, nor aſcend to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power, by commanding (the Law not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yet commanded it) that they whom you recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend be received, although neither the Parſon nor
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110951:8"/> Biſhop do approve of them; And that the Refuſers (according to the courſe ſo much formerly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of to have been uſed at the Councell Table) be not ſent for to attend to ſhew cauſe; At leaſt, that you would conſider conveniency, if not Law, and recommend none, but who are well known to you to be Orthodox, Learned, and Moderate, or at leaſt ſuch as have taken Orders, and are not notorious depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Book of Common Prayer; A care which appeareth by the Diſcourſes, Sermons and perſons of ſome recommended by you, not to have been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto taken, and it highly concerns both you in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the Common-wealth in the conſequences, that it ſhould have been taken; That neither one eſtate tranſact what is proper for two, nor two what is proper for three, and conſequently, that (contrary to Our declared will) Our Forts may not be ſeized; Our Arms may not be removed; Our Moneys may not be ſtopt; Our legall Directions may not be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termanded by you, nor We deſired to countermand them Our Self, nor ſuch entrances made upon a Reall War againſt Vs, upon pretence of an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie War againſt you, and a <hi>Chimaera</hi> of neceſſity. So far do you paſſe beyond your limits, whileſt you ſeem by your Demand to be ſtrangely ſtraitned within them. At leaſt We could have wiſht you would have expreſſed, what matters you meant as <hi>fit to be tranſacted onely in Parliament,</hi> and what you meant by <hi>onely in Parliament.</hi> You have (of late) been perſwaded by the new doctrines of ſome few to think that proper for your debates, which hath not uſed to be at all deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within thoſe wals, but been truſted wholly with Our Predeceſſors &amp; Vs, and to tranſact thoſe things
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110951:8"/> which without the Regall Authoritie, ſince there were Kings of this Kingdom were never tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: It therefore concerns Vs the more that you ſpeak out, and that both We and Our People may either know the bottom of your Demands, or know them to be bottomleſſe. What concerns more the Publike, and is more (indeed) proper for the high Court of Parliament, then the making of Laws? which not onely ought there to be tranſacted, but can be tranſacted no where elſe; but then you muſt admit Vs to be a part of the Parliament, you muſt not (as the ſenſe is of this part of this Demand, if it have any) deny the freedom of Our Anſwer, when We have as much right to reject what We think unreaſonable, as you have to propoſe what you think convenient or neceſſary; nor is it poſſible Our Anſwers either to Bills, or any other Propoſitions ſhould be wholly free, if We may not uſe the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every one of you, and of every Subject, and receive advice (without their danger who ſhall give it) from any perſon known or unknown, ſworn or unſworn, in theſe matters in which the Manage of Our Vote is truſted by the Law, to Our own Iudgement and Conſcience, which how beſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, is (and ever ſhall be) left likewiſe to Vs; and moſt unreaſonable it were that two Eſtates, propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſomething to the Third, that Third ſhould be bound to take no advice, whether it were fit to paſſe, but from thoſe two that did propoſe it. We ſhall ever in theſe things which are truſted wholly to Vs by the Law, not decline to hearken to the Advice of Our great Councell, and ſhall uſe to hear willingly the free debates of Our Privie Councell (whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110951:9"/> We may be ſuffered to have them for ſending for, and they ſhall not be terrified from that freedom, by Votes (and Brands of Malignants and Enemies to the State, for adviſing what no Law forbids to adviſe) but We will retain Our Power of admitting no more to any Councell then the Nature of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe requires, and of diſcourſing with whom We pleaſe, of what We pleaſe, and informing Our Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by debate with any Perſons, who may be well able to Inform and Adviſe Vs in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, though their Qualities, Education or other Abilities may not make them ſo fit to be of Our ſworn Councell, and not tye Our Self up not to hear any more then twenty five (and thoſe not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen abſolutely by Vs) out of a Kingdom ſo repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Iudicious and Experienced Perſons in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall kindes. And though We ſhall (with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Conſideration due to them) always weigh the Advices both of Our Great and Privie Councell, yet We ſhall alſo look upon their Advices, as Advices, not as Commands, or Impoſitions; upon them as Our Counſellours, not as Our Tutors and Guardians, and upon Our Self as their King, not as their Pupill, or Ward; for whatſoever of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality were by the Modeſty of Interpretation left in Vs in the firſt part of the ſecond Demand, as to the Parliament, is taken from Vs in the ſecond part of the ſame, and placed in this new fangled kinde of Councellours, whoſe power is ſuch and ſo expreſſed by it, that in all publike Acts concerning the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this Kingdom, which are proper for Our Privie Councell (for whoſe Advice all publike Acts are ſometimes proper, though never neceſſary) they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110951:9"/> are deſired to be admitted joynt Patentees with Vs in the Regality, and it is not plainly expreſſed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they mean Vs ſo much as a ſingle Vote in theſe Affairs: But it is plain they mean Vs no more at moſt then a ſingle Vote in them, and no more power then every one of the reſt of Our Fellow-Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; onely leave to Vs, out of their reſpect and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (and that onely is left of all Our ancient Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) a Choice, whether theſe that are thus to be joyned with (or rather ſet over) Vs, ſhall be fifteen, or twenty five, and great care is taken that the Oath which theſe Men ſhall take, ſhall be ſuch, in the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the forme of which (though ſure We are not wholly unconcerned in it) We may be wholly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that wholly reſerved to be agreed upon by both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew that no more Care is taken of Our ſafety, then of Our Power, after ſo great indignities offered to Vs, and countenanced by thoſe who were moſt obliged to reſent them: After Our Town and Fort kept from Vs (from which, if it were no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Ours then the whole Kingdom is, We can no more legally be kept out then out of Our whole Kingdom, which ſure your ſelves will not deny to be Treaſon) Our Arms, Our Goods ſent away, and Our Money ſtopt from Vs, Our Guards (in which We have no other Intention then to hinder the end of theſe things from being proportionable to their beginnings) are not onely deſired to be diſmiſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſatisfaction for the injurie, puniſhments of the injurers, and care taken for Our future Security from the like: But it is likewiſe deſired, (and for this Law is pretended, and might as well have been for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110951:10"/> the reſt, which yet with ſome ingenuity are it ſeems acknowledged to be but Deſires of Grace) that We ſhall not for the future raiſe any Guards or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Forces, but in caſe of actuall Rebellion or Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which if it had been Law, and ſo obſerved in the time of Our Famous Predeceſſours, few of thoſe Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories which have made this Nation famous in other parts, could have been legally atchieved, nor could Our bleſſed Predeceſſour Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> have ſo defended Her ſelf in <hi>88.</hi> And if no Forces muſt be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied till Rebellions and Invaſions (which will not ſtay for the calling of Parliaments, and their conſent for raiſing Forces) be actuall, they muſt undoubtedly (at leaſt moſt probably) be effectuall and prevalent.</p>
            <p>And as neither care is taken for Our Rights, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nor ſafety as a Prince, ſo Our Rights as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon are endeavoured to be had from Vs, it being asked, that it may be unlawfull and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not onely to <hi>conclude,</hi> but even to <hi>treat of any Marriage with any Perſon for Our own Children, or to place Governours about them, without conſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the intermiſſion of thoſe, without the conſent of Our good Lords of the Councell,</hi> that We may not onely be in a more defpicable ſtate then any of Our Predeceſſours, but in a meaner and viler condition then the loweſt of Our Subjects, who value no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty they have more, then that of the free Education and Marriage of their Children, from which We are asked to debar Our Self, and have the more reaſon to take it ill, that We are ſo, becauſe for Our choice of a Governour for Our Son, and of a Husband for Our Daughter, (in which the Proteſtant Religion was Our principall Conſideration) We conceived We
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110951:10"/> had reaſon to expect your preſent thanks, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of your future truſts.</p>
            <p>We ſuppoſe theſe Demands by this time to appear ſuch as the Demanders cannot be ſuppoſed to have any ſuch reall fear of Vs as hath been long pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they are too much in the ſtyle, not onely of equals, but of Conquerours, and as little to be intended for removing of Iealouſies (for which end they are ſaid to be asked, and that is not as Merchants ask at firſt much more then they will take, but as moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to effect it which (if they be) God help this poor Kingdom, and thoſe who are in the hands of ſuch Perſons, whoſe Iealouſies nothing elſe will remove) which indeed is ſuch a way, as if there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing differences and ſuits between two perſons, whereof one would have from the other ſeverall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of his ancient Land, he ſhould propoſe to him by way of Accommodation, that he would quit to him all thoſe in queſtion, with the reſt of his Eſtate, as the moſt neceſſary and effectuall means to remove all thoſe ſuits and differences. But we call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that as for Our Subjects ſake theſe Rights are veſted in Vs, ſo for their ſakes, as well as for Our own, We are reſolved not to quit them, nor to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, (though in a Parliamentary way) the ancient, equall, happy, well-poiſed and never-enough com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended Conſtitution of the Government of this Kingdom, nor to make Our Self of a King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> and this of a Kingdom a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique.</p>
            <p>There being three kindes of Government amongſt men, Abſolute Monarchy, Ariſtocracy and Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and all theſe having their particular conveniences
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110951:11"/> and inconveniencies. The experience and wiſdom of your Anceſtors hath ſo moulded this out of a mixture of theſe, as to give to this Kingdom (as far as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Prudence can provide) the conveniencies of all three, without the inconveniencies of any one, as long as the Balance hangs even between the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and they run joyntly on in their proper Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell (begetting Verdure and Fertility in the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows on both ſides) and the overflowing of either on either ſide raiſe no deluge or Inundation. The ill of abſolute Monarchy is Tyranny, the ill of Ariſtocracy is Faction and Diviſion, the ills of Democracy are Tumults, Violence and Licentiouſneſſe. The good of Monarchy is the uniting a Nation under one Head to reſiſt Invaſion from abroad, and Inſurrection at home: The good of Ariſtocracy is the Conjunction of Counſell in the ableſt Perſons of a State for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like benefit: The good of Democracy is Liberty, and the Courage and Induſtry which Liberty begetts.</p>
            <p>In this Kingdom the Laws are joyntly made by a King, by a Houſe of Peers, and by a Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons choſen by the People, all having free Votes and particular Priviledges: The Government ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe Laws is truſted to the King, Power of Treaties of War and Peace, of making Peers, of chuſing Officers and Councellours for State, Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for Law, Commanders for Forts and Caſtles, giving Commiſſions for raiſing men to make War abroad, or to prevent or provide againſt Invaſions or Inſurrections at home, benefit of Confiſcations, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of pardoning, and ſome more of the like kinde are placed in the King. And this kinde of regulated Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy having this power to preſerve that Authority,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110951:11"/> without which it would be diſabled to preſerve the Laws in their Force, and the Subjects in their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and proprieties, is intended to draw to him ſuch a Reſpect and Relation from the great Ones, as may hinder the ills of Diviſion and Faction, and ſuch a Fear and Reverence from the people, as may hinder Tumults, Violence and licentiouſneſſe. Again, that the Prince may not make uſe of this high and perpetuall power to the hurt of thoſe for whoſe good he hath it, and make uſe of the name of Publique Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie for the gain of his private Favourites and Followers, to the detriment of his People, the Houſe of Commons (an excellent Conſerver of Liberty, but never intended for any ſhare in Government, or the chuſing of them that ſhould govern) is ſolely intruſted with the firſt Propoſitions concerning the Leavies of Moneys (which is the ſinews as well of Peace as War) and the impeaching of thoſe, who for their own ends, though countenanced by any ſurreptiouſly gotten Command of the King, have violated that Law, which he is bound (when he knows it) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, and to the protection of which they were bound to adviſe him, at leaſt not to ſerve him in the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And the Lords being truſted with a Iudicatorie power, are an excellent Screen and Bank between the Prince and People, to aſſiſt each againſt any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of the other, and by juſt Iudgements to preſerve that Law, which ought to be the Rule of every one of the three. For the better enabling them in this, beyond the Examples of any of Our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, We were willingly contented to Oblige Our Self, both to call a Parliament every three yeers, and not to diſſolve it in fiftie dayes, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110951:12"/> exigent, the better to raiſe Money, and avoide the preſſure (no leſſe grievous to Vs then them) Our People muſt have ſuffered by a longer continuance of ſo vaſt a Charge as two great Armies, and for their greater certainty of having ſufficient time to remedy the inconveniencies ariſen during ſo long an abſence of Parliaments, and for the puniſhment of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and Miniſters of them, We yeelded up Our Right of diſſolving this Parliament, expecting an extraordinary moderation from it in gratitude for ſo unexampled a Grace, and little looking that any <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Partie</hi> ſhould have been encouraged or enabled to have perſwaded them, firſt to countenance the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtices and Indignities We have endured, and then by a new way of Satisfaction for what was taken from Vs, to demand of Vs at once to Confirm what was ſo taken, and to give up almoſt all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Since therefore the Power Legally placed in both Houſes is more then ſufficient to prevent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the power of Tyranny, and without the power which is now asked from Vs We ſhall not be able to diſcharge that Truſt which is the end of Monarchy, ſince this would be a totall Subverſion of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Laws, and that excellent Conſtitution of this Kingdom, which hath made this Nation ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeers both Famous and happy to a great degree of Envie; ſince to the power of puniſhing (which is already in your hands according to Law) if the power of Preferring be added, We ſhall have nothing left for Vs, but to look on; ſince the incroaching of one of theſe Eſtates upon the power of the other is unhappy in the effects both to them and all the reſt; ſince this power of at moſt a joynt Government in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110951:12"/> Vs with Our Councellors, (or rather Our Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) will return Vs to the worſt kinde of Minority, and make Vs deſpicable both at home and abroad, and beget eternall Factions and Diſſentions (as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to publike Happineſſe as War) both in the choſen, and the Houſes that chuſe them, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who chuſe the Chuſers; ſince ſo new a power will undoubtedly intoxicate perſons who were not born to it, and beget not onely Diviſions among them as equals, but in them contempt of Vs as become an equall to them, and Inſolence and Injuſtice towards Our people, as now ſo much their inferiors, which will be the more grievous unto them, as ſuffering from thoſe who were ſo lately of a neerer degree to themſelves, and being to have redreſſe onely from thoſe that placed them, and fearing they may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to preſerve what they have made, both out of kindeneſſe and policie; ſince all great changes are extreamly inconvenient, and almoſt infallibly beget yet greater Changes, which beget yet greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies.</p>
            <p>Since as great an one in the Church muſt follow this of the Kingdom; Since the ſecond Eſtate would in all probability follow the Fate of the firſt, and by ſome of the ſame turbulent ſpirits Iealouſies would be ſoon raiſed againſt them, and the like Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for reconciliation of Differences would be then ſent to them, as they now have joyned to ſend to Vs, till (all Power being veſted in the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and their number making them incapable of tranſacting Affairs of State with the neceſſary Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie and expedition; thoſe being retruſted to ſome cloſe Committee) at laſt the Common people (who in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110951:13"/> the mean time muſt be flattered, and to whom Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence muſt be given in all their wilde humours, how contrary ſoever to eſtabliſhed Law, or their own reall Good) diſcover this <hi>Arcanum Imperii,</hi> That all this was done by them, but not for them, grow weary of Iourney-work, and ſet up for themſelves, call Parity and Independence, Liberty; devour that Eſtate which had devoured the reſt; Deſtroy all Rights and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties, all diſtinctions of Families and Merit; And by this means this ſplendid and excellently diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed form of Government end in a dark equall <hi>Chaos</hi> of Confuſion, and the long Line of Our many noble Anceſtors in a <hi>Jack Cade,</hi> or a <hi>Wat Tyler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all theſe Reaſons to all theſe demands Our Anſwer is, <hi>Nolumus Leges Angliae mutari:</hi> But this We promiſe, that We will be as carefull of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lawes in what is ſuppoſed to concerne whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Our Subjects, as in what moſt concernes Our ſelfe: For indeed We profeſſe to beleeve, that the preſervation of every Law concernes Vs, thoſe of obedience being not ſecure, when thoſe of protection are violated; And We being moſt of any injured in the leaſt violation of that, by which We enjoy the higheſt Rghts and greateſt Benefits, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obliged to defend no leſſe by Our intereſt then by Our duty, and hope that no Iealouſies to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſhall be any longer nouriſhed in any of Our good People, by the ſubtill inſinuations, and ſecret practices of men, who for private ends are diſaffected to Our Honour and Safety, and the Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Our People. And to ſhew you, that no juſt indignation at ſo reproachfull offers ſhall make Vs refuſe to grant what is probable to conduce to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110951:13"/> the good of Our good People, becauſe of the ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it comes in, We will ſearch carefully in this heap of unreaſonable Demands, for ſo much as We may (complying with Our Conſcience, and the duty of Our Truſt) aſſent unto, and ſhall accordingly agree to it.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of which Search, in the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, under a Demand which would take from Vs that truſt which God, Nature, and the Laws of the Land have placed in Vs, and of which none of you could endure to be deprived; We finde ſomething to which We give this Anſwer, That We have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the principall places about Our Children to perſons of Quality, Integrity and Piety, with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall regard that their Tender yeers might be ſo ſeaſoned with the Principles of the true Proteſtant Religion, as (by the bleſſing of God upon this Our care) this whole Kingdom may in due time reap the fruit thereof: And as We have been likewiſe very carefull in the choice of Servants about them, that none of them may be ſuch, as by ill Principles, or by ill Examples to croſſe Our endeavours for their Pious and Vertuous Education, ſo if there ſhall be found (for all Our care to prevent it) any perſon about Our Children (or about Vs, which is more then you ask) <hi>againſt whom both Houſes</hi> ſhall make appear to Vs <hi>any juſt exception,</hi> We ſhall not onely <hi>remove</hi> them, but thank you for the Information; Onely We ſhall expect, that you ſhall be likewiſe carefull that there be no under-hand dealing by any to ſeek faults, to make room for others to ſucceed in their places.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> Demand, as We will not ſuffer any to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110951:14"/> ſhare with Vs in our power of Treaties, which are moſt improper for Parliaments, and leaſt in thoſe Treaties in which We are neerlyeſt concerned, not onely as a King but as a Father, yet We do (ſuch is Our deſire to give all reaſonable ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) aſſure you by the word of a King, that We ſhall never propoſe or entertaine any Treaty whatſoever for the marriage of any of Our Children, without due regard to the true Proteſtant Profeſſion, the good of Our Kingdoms, and the Honour of Our Family.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> Demand, concerning <hi>the Lawes in force againſt Jeſuites, Prieſts, and Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> We have by many of Our Meſſages to you, by Our voluntary promiſe to you, ſo ſolemnly made never to pardon any Popiſh Prieſt, by Our ſtrict Proclamations lately publiſhed in this point, and by the publike Examples which we have made in that caſe ſince Our Reſidence at <hi>York,</hi> &amp; before at <hi>London</hi> ſufficiently expreſſed Our zeal herein. Why do you then ask that in which Our own Inclination hath prevented you? And if you can yet finde any more effectuall Courſe to diſable them from Diſturbing the State or eluding the Law by truſts or otherwiſe, We ſhall willingly give Our Conſent to it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> concerning <hi>the Votes of Popiſh Lords,</hi> We underſtand that they in diſcretion have withdrawn themſelves from the Service of the Houſe of Peers, (&amp; had done ſo when uſe was publikely made of their names to aſperſe the Votes of that Houſe, which was then counted as Malignant as thoſe (who are called <hi>Our Unknown and Unſworne Councellors</hi>) are now) neither doe We conceive that ſuch a Poſitive Law againſt the Votes of any whoſe blood gives them that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110951:14"/> right, is ſo proper in regard of the Priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but are content, that ſo long as they ſhall not be conformable to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they ſhall not be admitted to ſit in the Houſe of Peers, but onely to give their Prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies to ſuch Proteſtant Lords as they ſhall chuſe, who are to diſpoſe of them as they themſelves ſhall think fit, without any Reference at all to the Giver.</p>
            <p>As to the deſires for <hi>a Bill for the Education of the Children of Papiſts by Proteſtants in the Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> many about Vs can witneſſe with Vs, That We have often delivered Our Opinion, that ſuch a Courſe (with Gods bleſſing upon it) would be the moſt effect all for the rooting out of Popery out of this Kingdom; We ſhall therefore thank you for it, and encourage you in it, and, when it comes unto Vs, do Our Dutie; And We heartily wiſh, for the publike good, that the time you have ſpent in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Ordinances without Vs, had been imployed in preparing this and other good Bills for Vs.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> touching <hi>The Reformation to be made of the Church Government and Liturgie,</hi> We had hoped, that what We had formerly declared concerning the ſame, had been ſo ſufficiently underſtood by you and all good Subjects, that We ſhould not need to have expreſſed Our Self further in it. We told you in Our Anſwers to your Petition preſented to Vs at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> the firſt of December, <hi>That for any il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall Innovations which may have crept in, We ſhould willingly concur in the removall of them; That if Our Parliament ſhould adviſe Us to call a Nationall Synode, which may duely examine ſuch Ceremonies as give juſt cauſe of Offence to any, We ſhould take it into Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110951:15"/> and apply Our Self to give due ſatisfaction therein; That We were perſwaded in Our Conſcience, that no Church could be found upon the Earth, that profeſſeth the true Religion with more purity of Doctrine, then the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth, nor where the Government and Diſcipline are joyntly more beautified, and free from Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, then as they are here eſtabliſhed by Law;</hi> which (by the grace of God We will with Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie maintain (while We live) in their Purity and Glory, not onely againſt all Invaſions of Popery, but alſo from the Irreverence of thoſe many Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Separatiſts, wherewith of late this Kingdom and Our City of <hi>London</hi> abounds, to the great diſhonour and hazard both of Church and State; For the ſuppreſſion of whom We required your timely and active aſſiſtance. We told you in Our firſt Declaration, printed by the advice of Our Privie Councell, <hi>That for differences amongſt our ſelves for matters indifferent in their own nature concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, We ſhould in tenderneſſe to any number of Our loving Subjects very willingly comply with the advice of Our Parliament, that ſome Law might be made for the exemption of tender Conſciences from puniſhment or proſecution for ſuch Ceremonies, and in ſuch Caſes, which by the judgement of moſt men are held to be matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and of ſome to be abſolutely unlawfull; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that this eaſe ſhould be attempted and purſued with that modeſtie, temper, and ſubmiſſion, that in the mean time the Peace and quiet of the Kingdom be not diſturbed, the Decencie and Comelineſſe of Gods Service diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, nor the Pious, Sober, Devout actions of thoſe Reverend Perſons who were the firſt Labourers in the bleſſed Reformation, or of that time, be ſcandalled and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110951:15"/> defamed.</hi> And We heartily wiſh, that others whom it concerned, had been as ready (as their duty bound them, though they had not received it from Vs) to have purſued this Caution, as We were, and ſtill are willing and readie to make good every particular of that Promiſe. Nor did We onely appear willing to joyn in ſo good a Work, when it ſhould be brought Vs, but preſt and urged you to it by Our Meſſage of the fourteenth of February in theſe words, <hi>And becauſe His Majeſtie obſerves great and different troubles to ariſe in the hearts of His People, concerning the Government and Liturgie of the Church, His Majeſtie is willing to declare, That He will refer the whole conſideration to the wiſdom of His Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which He deſires them to enter into ſpeedily, that the preſent diſtractions about the ſame may be compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but deſires not to be preſſed to any ſingle Act on His part, till the whole be ſo digeſted and ſetled by both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that His Majeſtie may cleerly ſee what is fit to be left, as well as what is fit to be taken away:</hi> Of which We the more hoped of a good ſucceſſe to the generall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Our People, becauſe you ſeem in this Propoſition to deſire but <hi>a Reformation,</hi> and not (as is daily preached for as neceſſary in thoſe many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles which have within theſe nineteen moneths begun to ſwarm, and which, though their Leaders differ from you in this opinion, yet appear to many as countenanced by you, by not being puniſhed by you, (few elſe, by reaſon of the Order of the Houſe of Commons of the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of September, daring to do it) a deſtruction of the preſent Diſcipline and Liturgie. And We ſhall moſt cheerfully <hi>give Our beſt aſſiſtance for raiſing a ſufficient maintenance for preaching Miniſters,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:110951:16"/> in ſuch courſe as ſhall be moſt for the encouragement and advancement of Piety and Learning.</p>
            <p>For the Bills you mention, and the Conſultation you intimate, knowing nothing of the particular matters of the one (though We like the Titles well) nor of the manner of the other, but from an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (to whom We give little credit, and We wiſh no man did more) Common fame, We can ſay nothing till We ſee them.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> We would not have the <hi>Oath of all Privy Councellors and Judges</hi> ſtraitned to particular Statutes of one or two particular Parliaments, but extend to all Statutes of all Parliaments, and the whole Law of the Land, and ſhall willingly conſent <hi>that an enquirie of all the breaches and violations of the Law may be given in charge by the Juſtices of the Kings Bench every Terme, and by the Judges of Aſſize in their Circuits, and Juſtices of Peace at the Seſſions to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and puniſhed according to Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> We ſhall ever be moſt ready, (and We are ſorry it ſhould be thought needfull to move Vs to it) not onely to joyn with any (particularly <hi>with the States of the united Provinces,</hi> of which We have given a late proof in the Match of Our Daughter) <hi>for the defence and maintenance of Proteſtant Religion, againſt all deſignes and attempts of the Pope and his adherents,</hi> but ſingly (if need were) to oppoſe with Our life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune <hi>all ſuch Deſignes</hi> in all other Nations, were they joyned: And that for Conſiderations of Conſcience, far more then any temporall end <hi>of obtaining acceſſe of ſtrength and reputation,</hi> or any naturall end <hi>of reſtoring Our Royall Siſter and her Princely Iſſue to their Dignities and Dominions,</hi> though theſe be likewiſe much conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by Vs.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110951:16"/>
            <p>For the <hi>18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> It was not Our fault, that an Act was not paſſed <hi>to cleer the Lord <hi>Kymbolton,</hi> and the five Members of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> but yours, who inſerted ſuch Clauſes into both the Preamble and Act (perhaps perſwaded to it by ſome who wiſh not that you ſhould in any thing receive ſatisfaction from Vs) as by paſſing the Preamble We muſt have wounded Our Honour againſt Our Conſcience, and by another Clauſe have admitted a Conſequence, from which We could never have been ſecured, by declaring, <hi>That no Member of either Houſe, upon any Accuſation of Treaſon, could have his Perſon ſeized with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conſent of that Houſe, of which he is a Member,</hi> though the known Law be, <hi>That Priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament extends not to Treaſon,</hi> and if it did, any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (the Houſe being for a ſhort time adjourned, and ſo their Conſent not being ſo had) how treaſonable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Intentions were, how cleerly ſoever known, and how ſuddenly ſoever to be executed, muſt have fair leave given him to go on and purſue them, no way, how Legall ſoever, after the paſſing ſuch a Clauſe, being left to prevent it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, We Conjure you and all Men to reſt ſatisfied with the Truth of Our Profeſſions, and the Reality of Our Intentions; not to aſk ſuch things as deny themſelves; That you Declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tumults, and puniſh the Authours; That you allow Vs Our Propriety in Our Towns, Arms and Goods, and Our Share in the Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Power, which would be counted in Vs, not onely breach of Priviledge, but Tyranny and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Parliaments to deny to you: And when you ſhall have given Vs ſatisfaction upon thoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110951:17"/> Perſons who have taken away the One, and recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thoſe Declarations (particularly that of the <hi>26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>May</hi>) and thoſe in the point of the <hi>Militia,</hi> (Our juſt Rights, wherein We will no more part with then with Our Crown, leſt We inable others by them to take that from Vs) which would take away the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and declined the beginnings of a War againſt Vs, under pretence of Our Intention of making One againſt you: as We have never oppoſed the firſt part of the <hi>13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> Demand, ſo We ſhall be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with you in the latter.</p>
            <p>And being then confident that the Credit of thoſe Men, who deſire a generall Combuſtion, will be ſo weakned with you, that they will not be able to do this Kingdom any more harm, We ſhall be willing to grant Our generall Pardon, with ſuch Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as ſhall be thought fit, and ſhall receive much more joy in the hope of a full and conſtant Happineſſe of Our People in the True Religion, and under the Protection of the Law, by a bleſſed Vnion between Vs and Our Parliament (ſo much deſired by Vs) then in any ſuch increaſe of Our Own Revenue (how much ſoever beyond former Grants) as (when Our Subjects were wealthieſt) Our Parliament could have ſetled upon Vs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110951:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
